Studer, Norman; Papers apap116
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Photographs, ca. 1934-ca. 1970; Undated; 5; 3.21 cubic ft.
  - School Photographs, ca. 1934-ca.1970; Undated; 5.1
    - Downtown Community School, Annual Art Show, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 1)
    - Downtown Community School, Art Classes, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 1)
    - Downtown Community School, Chief Red Thunder Cloud, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 2)
    - Downtown Community School, Field Trips, 1964; Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 3)
    - Downtown Community School, Field Trips, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 4-6)
    - Downtown Community School, Folk Dancing, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 7-10)
    - Downtown Community School, Musical Performances, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 11)
    - Downtown Community School, Old Merchant's House Christmas Performance, 1965; Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 1)
    - Downtown Community School, Plays and Performances, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 2)
    - Downtown Community School, Poetry Reading, ca. 1970 (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 3)
    - Downtown Community School, Sojourner Truth, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 4)
    - Downtown Community School, Students, 1962; Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 5)
    - Elisabeth Irwin High School Visit to Upstate New York, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 6)
    - Little Red School House New Jersey Trip, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 7)
    - Little Red School House, Norman Studer's First Class, ca. 1933 (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 8)
    - Studer, Norman, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 9)
  - Camp Woodland Photographs, ca. 1938-1958; Undated; 5.2
    The Camp Woodland photographs subseries documents the activities of the campers, the Folk Festivals of the Catskills, and many of the Catskill indigenes, including Dick and George Edwards, Harry Robinson, Grant Rogers, Ernie Sagan, Harry Siemsen, Orson Slack, and George Van Kleeck. There are a number of photographs of Norman Cazden and Herbert Haufrecht, both of whom served as musical directors for the camp, photographs of Norman Studer, as well as photographs of Pete Seeger playing his banjo. There is a file of photographs of Camp Hilltop as well.
    Former camper Joan Simon Faulkner also donated digitized versions of many of her black and white and color photographs from Camp Woodland from 1954, 1960, and 1962 and of the 1958 Folk Festival of the Catskills. Please contact the Department to access these.
    - Activities, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 1-2)
    - Animals, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 3)
    - Animals, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 2)
    - Artwork, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 4)
    - Artwork, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 3)
    - Athletics, 1957; Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 5)
    - Athletics, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 4)
    - Camp and Area Buildings, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 6)
    - Camp and Area Buildings, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 5)
    - Camp Hilltop, ca. 1938-1939 (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 7)
    - Camper and Staff Portraits, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 8-9)
    - Camper and Staff Portraits, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 6)
    - Campfires, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 10)
    - Catskill Residents, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 11)
    - Cazden, Norman and Herbert Haufrecht, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 12)
    - Chorus, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 13)
    - Cooking and Meals, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 14)
    - Cooking and Meals, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 7)
    - Crafts, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 15)
    - Crafts, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 8)
    - Dramatics, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 16)
    - Edwards, Dick, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 17)
    - Edwards, George, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 18)
    - Flag Raising, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 19)
    - Folk Festival of the Catskills, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 20-22)
    - Folk Festival of the Catskills, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 9)
    - Gardening, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 23)
    - Hikes, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 24)
    - Hecht, Nova, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 25)
    - Masquerade, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 26)
    - Meetings, including Parent Visits, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 27)
    - Museum, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 28)
    - Oxen, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 29)
    - Performances, including Folk Dancing, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 30)
    - Performances, including Folk Dancing, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 10)
    - Photocopies of Photographs from Camp Woodland, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 31)
    - Photographs Donated by the Maine Folklife Center, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 32)
    - Postcards, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 33)
    - Pagan, Susan, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 34)
    - Robinson, Harry, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 35)
    - Rogers, Grant, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 36)
    - Sagan, Ernie, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 37)
    - Scanned Photographs from Joan Cooper's Album, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 1)
    - Scenery and Landmarks, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 2)
    - Science, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 3)
    - Science, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook, Carolyn Kopperl Bensinger, 1949; 1954; Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, Sara Abramson, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 5)
    - Scrapbook, Unidentified, 1952; 1957; Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 6)
    - Seeger, Pete, ca. 1950 (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 7)
    - Siemsen, Harry, 1958; Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 8)
    - Slack, Orson, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 9)
    - Studer with Campers and Guests, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 12)
    - Swimming, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 10-11)
    - Swimming, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 13)
    - Todd, Mike, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 12)
    - Trips, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 13)
    - Van Kleeck, George, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 14)
    - Van Wagner, Etson, Undated (Box 3 (5-Photographs), Folder 1)
    - Visiting with Catskill Region Residents, Undated (Box 3 (5-Photographs), Folder 2)
    - V-J Day, ca. 1945 (Box 3 (5-Photographs), Folder 3)
    - War Related Activities, ca. 1942-1945 (Box 3 (5-Photographs), Folder 4)
    - Woodworking, Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 9)
    - Working Outdoors, 1957-1958; Undated (Box 3 (5-Photographs), Folder 5)
    - Working Outdoors, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 14)
    - Yale, Marvin, Undated (Box 3 (5-Photographs), Folder 6)
  - General Images, Undated; 5.3
    This subseries consists of a small number of general photographs and postcards, many likely taken or acquired on trips.
    - Bowne House, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 1)
    - Catskill Postcards, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 2)
    - Darling, Johnny and Martha Ann, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 3)
    - Doolittle, Frank Wesley, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 4)
    - Fishing, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 5)
    - Gaspard de Coligny, Colonel William, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 6)
    - Homes Torn Down for Reservoir Development, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 7)
    - IBM Building, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 8)
    - Michigan, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 9)
    - Old Stone Aqueduct, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 15)
    - Peeling and Piling Hemlock Bark for Prattsville Tannery, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 10)
    - Post Cards, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 11)
    - Stone Structure, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 12)
    - Trip to Gaspee, Undated (Box 1 (5-Photographs), Folder 13)
    - Unidentified Locations, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified Performance, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 1)
    - Unidentified Portraits, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 2)
    - Unidentified Portraits, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified Trips by Norman Studer, some possibly the Catskills, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 3)
    - Unidentified Work Crew, Undated (Oversized 2, Folder 18)
    - Village with Thatched Roof Homes, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 4)
    - Water Supply, Ashokan Construction, Undated (Box 2 (5-Photographs), Folder 5)
- Audio Recordings, 1944-1970; Undated; 6
  This series contains audio recordings of special events and everyday activities at the Downtown Community School and Camp Woodland. The Department digitized hundreds of reel-to-reel audio recordings to date.
  - Downtown Community School, 1952-1970; Undated; 6.1
    The Downtown Community School audio recordings document guest speakers, student discussions and readings, school plays, intergroup conferences, lectures, staff meetings, musical performances, school trips, oral histories and other programs. Highlights of the subseries include recordings about race relations and the boycott that took place at the Lincoln School in Englewood, NJ in February 1963 and a visit to the school from Red Thunder Cloud, last Indigenous speaker of the Catawba language. Not all recordings are identified or dated.
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of woman..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of woman..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1969 October 10
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1969 October 10
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 March
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1969 May 19
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1966 February
    - This is a Downtown Community School (DCS)..., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1970 January 30
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of Frank..., 1964 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1964 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording Ann..., 1958 March 15
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1960 March 19
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1961 June 6
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1969 July 16
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1969 May 19
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1962 May 10
    - Second Revolution in the Schools, 1963 November 23
    - This is a Downtown Community School (DCS)..., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of Harry..., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1964 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., Undated
    - This is a Downtown Community School (DCS)..., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1952 May 9
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording with..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording with..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1963 January
    - Englewood, NJ School Boycott & Nancy Bloch Meeting, circa 1963 February
    - Second Revolution in the Schools, 1963 November 23
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1964 May 13
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording with..., 1962 April 6
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1966 February
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 March
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 March 2
    - This is a Downtown Community School (DCS)..., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1963 January 18
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1970 April 29
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1969 May 19
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a..., 1964 May 15
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a..., 1964 May 15
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of folk..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of 7th..., 1964 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1964 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of eight..., 1962 April 6
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of an..., 1959 February 15
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1969 May 19
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1958 March 15
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1962 May 10
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1963 January 18
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1970 January 30
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 March
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 March
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1964 March 5
    - This is a Downtown Community School (DCS)..., Undated
    - This is a Downtown Community School (DCS)..., Undated
    - Red Thunder cloud with 7th grade and staff meeting at DCS, Undated
    - This is a Downtown Community School (DCS)..., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a..., 1960 October 12
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1964 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a DCS..., 1964 October
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of their..., 1963 November 22
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1963 December
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1964 March 5
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1960 March 18
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording. Founded..., 1965 March 2
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of DCS..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of DCS..., 1963 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1959 January
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a..., 1964 October
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a..., 1964 October
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of the..., 1960 March 19
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of..., 1969 July 16
    - Red Thunder Cloud reminisces about his past., Undated
    - Downtown Community School (DCS) recording of a..., 1960 October 12
    - Englewood, NJ School Boycott & Nancy Bloch Meeting, circa 1963 February
  - Camp Woodland, 1944-1962; Undated; 2
    The Camp Woodland audio recordings may be one of the more significant components of the collection. While at Camp Woodland, Norman Studer recorded numerous oral histories of many of the indigenous Catskill residents as well as the annual Folk Festival of the Catskills. Studer was acutely aware that he was in a position to capture the ethnographic folk culture, music, and ecology of a fading era. In many instances, the tapes represent the only extant recordings and variations of a number of songs.
    Highlights of the Camp Woodland audio recordings include Pete Seeger and Bessie Jones performing at the Folk Festival of the Catskills and at Camp Woodland. A July 1962 recording documents counselor Hector Angula teaching Seeger Guantanamara for the first time and a discussion of the lyrics of the song by the two men.
    Not all recordings are identified or dated.
    - Norman Studer discusses and conducts interviews..., Undated
    - Original recording consists of Peter Seeger..., Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1948, 1948 August 21
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1957, 1957 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1959, 1959 August 14
    - A banquet at Camp Woodland, Phoenicia, N.Y., Side..., 1954 August 23
    - A banquet at Camp Woodland, Phoenicia, N.Y., Side..., 1954 August 23
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1960, Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1959, 1959 August 15
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1959, 1959 August 14
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, July 15, 1962, 1962 July 15
    - Interview of Bessie Jones at Camp Woodland...., 1950 August
    - George Edwards singing at Camp Woodland,..., Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1957, 1957 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1953, 1953 August 15
    - Original recording consists of Peter Seeger..., 1960 July 31
    - Joe Hickerson..., 1955 January
    - A banquet at Camp Woodland, Phoenicia, N.Y., Side..., 1954 August 23
    - Interview of Bessie Jones at Camp Woodland...., 1961 July
    - Norman Studer discusses and conducts interviews..., Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1947, 1947 August 21
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1957, 1957 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1958, 1958 August 16-17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1959, 1959 August 14
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1961, 1961 July
    - A banquet at Camp Woodland, Phoenicia, N.Y., Side..., 1954 August 23
    - Children's songs and stories gathered as..., Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1957, 1957 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1956, 1956 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1959, 1959 August 15
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1959, 1959 August 14
    - Original recording consists of Peter Seeger..., 1960 July
    - Folk Festival of the Catskills at Camp Woodland,..., Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1948, 1948 August 21
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1953, 1953 August 15
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1959, 1959 August 14
    - Bessie Jones singing at Camp Woodland...., 1961 July
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1961, 1961 July
    - Pete Seeger singing "Old Joe Clark" at Camp..., 1955 January
    - Original recording consists of Peter Seeger..., Undated
    - Babatunde Olatunji at Camp Woodland's Annual Folk..., Undated
    - Babatunde Olatunji at Camp Woodland's Annual Folk..., Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1958, 1958 August 16-17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, August 15th 1953 130, 1953 August 15
    - Original recording consists of Peter Seeger..., 1960 July 31
    - Interview of Bessie Jones at Camp Woodland...., 1962 July
    - Interviews with George Edwards and Orson Slack at..., 1944 June 30
    - Interview of Bessie Jones at Camp Woodland...., 1962 July
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1956, 1956 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1960, 1960 August 14
    - Songs of George Edwards recorded at camp Woodland,..., 1948 July
    - Norman Studer discusses and conducts interviews..., Undated
    - Mary Robinson interview at Camp Woodland,..., Undated
    - Norman Studer discusses and conducts interviews..., Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1960, Undated
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1960, 1960 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1957, 1957 August 17
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1960, 1960 August 14
    - Folk Music of the Catskills, 1952, 1962 August 15
- Films, ca. 1946-1962; Undated; 7; 9 films
  Arranged chronologically.
  The film series contains nine 16mm and 8mm films, many of which record activities at Camp Woodland. Also included is a film of the 1951 graduation ceremonies at the Downtown Community School and a copy of the Jules Victor Schwerin film Indian Summer. Films 1-8 were reformatted and are available for viewing in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives' research room. All requests to view this series should be made in advance of a researcher's visit to the Department.
  - Untitled Woodland Film, ca. 1946; 18 minutes Black and White; genreform: 16mm (Film 1)
    Film contains Camp Woodland activities including: a Sunday meeting at the amphitheater, swimming pool, baseball, long jump, badminton, guitar player (Don Muffson?), whittling, painting, typing, camp store or mailroom, hot dogs on an open fire, campers hiking, local houses, construction of a dam or reservoir (5:00), George Edwards, chopping wood, campers interviewing local residents, Prattsville sign, man in horsedrawn haywagon, campers returning to camp with a woman's spinning wheel, campers swimming at falls, campers rebuilding the amphitheater, sharpening blades, whittling, George Edwards, Norman Cazden conducting children singing, Camp Woodland 4H Club, footrace, Museum of Farm Implements, and the Seventh Annual Folk Festival of the Catskills which included dancing, singing, and George Van Kleek.
  - Untitled Woodland Film, ca. 1946; 4 minutes, 20 seconds Black and White; genreform: 16mm (Film 2)
    Camp Woodland activities including some duplication of Film 1. Activities include: people visiting camp, an audience of adults and campers watching performances, campers performing, campers playing sports, campers making their beds, camp buildings, and campers packing to leave camp for the summer.
  - Untitled Downtown Community School Film, 1951; 3 minutes Black and White; genreform: 16mm (Film 3)
    Graduation ceremony at the Downtown Community School in 1951. Includes: graduates entering, musical performances, awarding of diplomas, graduates processing out, the audience leaving, and the refreshment table.
  - Indian Summer, 1960; 28 minutes Black and White; genreform: 16mm (Film 4)
    From Folkfilms. Producer and director, Jules Victor Schwerin; scenario, Peggy Lawson, Jules Schwerin; narration, Jules Schwerin, Lawrence Weinberg; narrator, Jared Reed; music score, Peter Seeger, Michael Seeger; editor, Peggy Lawson; director of photography, associate producer, Julius Tannenbaum; additional photography, Max Glenn, Milek Knebel; narrator, Jared Reed; Catskill folklorist, Norman Studer. Participants: Robert circa Gregory (old man), Ralph Vanderlip (boy), Grant Rodgers (fiddler), Walter L. Terry (judge), David and Herta Marshall (singers), the people of Cannonsville, Delhi, Deposit, Granton, Rock Rift, Walton, West Branch, Delaware River, State of New York.
    On the first hot day of summer, an old farmer goes fishing just as he has done for many years on the West Branch of the Delaware River. A young boy, his frequent fishing companion, eagerly takes him to see the first giant bulldozers, which are to begin construction on the Cannonsville Reservoir. In order to provide more water for the cities, the vast project will flood the valley. The old man goes to the general store and walks the length of the valley to talk about his concerns, but most people do not support him. The young people of the valley celebrate at a barn dance. The old man resists eviction with his unloaded flintlock. The next day, he watches as the houses and farms are burned to clear the way.
  - Untitled Woodland Film, 1960; 11 minutes Color; genreform: 8mm (Film 5)